Guide to the Anna Schwartz Papers, 1929-2012 RL.01152
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Anna Schwartz papers
1929-2012
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.01152
23 Linear Feet
0.08 Gigabytes
Economist at the National Bureau of Economic Research and collaborator with Milton Friedman on numerous works, including A Monetary History of the United States, 1867-1960. Schwartz also served as the executive director of the United States Gold Commission from 1981 to 1982. Collection consists largely of Schwartz's professional materials, including economics research and subject files on monetary policy, gold, the Federal Reserve, currency, and the 2008 Financial Crisis; collaborations with other economists; correspondence, largely professional but including some personal letters; Gold Commission materials from the 1980s; Shadow Open Market Committee materials; and writings, including lectures and articles by Schwartz. Another significant part of the collection is the Milton Friedman series, which includes correspondence, writings, and other materials relating to Friedman and his work.
17500 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Electronic records in this collection have been migrated to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access, please contact Research Services before coming to use these records.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Anna Schwartz Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2012.
Historical Note
Anna Jacobson Schwartz was born in the Bronx in 1915, and attended Barnard College. She initially worked for the U.S. Dept. of Agriculture and the Social Science Research Council, but moved to the National Bureau of Economic Research in 1941 and remained there until her death in 2012.
Chronology List
1915 Nov. 10 Born in the Bronx, NY, to Hillel Jacobson and Pauline Shainmark. Her birthday began to be celebrated on Nov. 11 after 1918, when Nov. 11 became a holiday.
1934 B.A., Barnard College, Phi Beta Kappa
1935 M.A., Columbia University
1936 Worked at the Dept. of Agriculture
1936 Married Isaac Schwartz
1936-1941 Worked at Columbia University Social Science Research Council
1941 Joined the National Bureau of Economic Research
1953 Co-wrote Growth and Fluctuations in the British Economy, 1790-1850: An Historical, Statistical, and Theoretical Study of Britain's Economic Development, with A. Gayer and W.W. Rostow
1963 Co-wrote A Monetary History of the United States, 1867-1960, with Milton Friedman
1964 Ph.D., Columbia University
1967-1969 Adjunct Professor of Economics at City University of New York
1969-1970 Adjunct Professor of Economics at New York University
1970 Co-wrote Monetary Statistics of the United States: Estimates, Sources, Methods, with Milton Friedman
1981-1982 Staff Director of U.S. Gold Commission
1982 Co-wrote Monetary Trends in the United States and the United Kingdom: Their Relation to Income, Prices, and Interest Rates, 1867-1975, with Milton Friedman
1983 Co-wrote The International Transmission of Inflation, with M.R. Darby
1984 Co-wrote A Retrospective on the Classical Gold Standard, 1821-1931, with Michael Bordo
1987 Wrote Money in Historical Perspective
1987 Co-edited The Search for Stable Money: Essays on Monetary Reform, with James A. Dorn
1987-1988 President of the Western Economic Association
1992 Edited Commodity Monies
2012 June 21 Died following a long illness, NY
Collection Overview
The Anna Schwartz Papers consists largely of Schwartz's professional materials and has been divided into 9 series and 1 file: Correspondence, Personal Materials, Conferences, Subject and Research Files, Writings, Gold Commission, Shadow Open Market Committee, Milton Friedman Materials, Writings by Others, and Electronic Materials.
Schwartz's Correspondence ranges from her college years through 2012, with the majority of material dating from the 2000s. Correspondence has been arranged chronologically and largely reflects Schwartz's research interests and collaborations with other economists. Particularly in her later years, Schwartz saved various email forwards and printouts on news and economics sent from her correspondents, and those materials are also kept in the Correspondence series. Milton Friedman's correspondence is held in the Milton Friedman Series.
Another significant portion of the collection is Schwartz's Subject and Research Files, which include materials on economics, monetary policy, banking, various countries, the Federal Reserve and its many activities, foreign exchange rates and intervention, currency, and many other miscellaneous topics. This series has been arranged alphabetically and has overlaps with other series in the collection, including Schwartz's Writings and Correspondence series.
The majority of Schwartz's Writings series related to various lectures and articles by Schwartz, although the series does contain some drafts and edited works from Schwartz's books as well as accompanying material such as appendices or editor correspondence. It has been arranged chronologically, with Schwartz's book reviews consolidated at the beginning of the series. Writings by Friedman, including collaborations between Friedman and Schwartz, are housed in the Milton Friedman Series.
Writings By Others is large series that includes drafts and final versions of articles collected or sent to Schwartz by colleagues. Most of these relate to Schwartz's research interests. This series also includes reader reports by Schwartz for various articles. It has been arranged alphabetically by author.
Three series reflect Schwartz's professional service. The Conferences Series reflects Schwartz's attendance and involvement in various economic conferences throughout her career. It is arranged alphabetically by conference. The Shadow Open Market Committee Series is a small series reflecting her service on the committee in the 2000s. It includes meeting materials as well as papers presented by Schwartz and other committee members. The Gold Commission Series encompasses materials from Schwartz's service as executive director of the Gold Commission from 1981 to 1982, and includes reports and research materials on gold and the gold standard; drafts, comments, and copies of the final report; and correspondence from the committee and the general public on issues regarding gold.
The Milton Friedman Materials Series includes all materials in the Schwartz Papers that relate to Milton Friedman and Schwartz's work with him, including joint writings and collaborations. Correspondence from Friedman is housed in this series. It also includes a large number of Friedman's writings, such as his columns for Newsweek and Wall Street Journal, and articles and talks by Friedman that Schwartz collected over the years. Some of these were drafts or working papers sent to Schwartz by Friedman for comments. Another portion of the series is the Writings About Friedman sub-series, which includes news clippings, essays, Nobel Prize coverage, and obituaries and memorials.
The Personal Materials Series includes Schwartz's Barnard College materials, interviews and clippings about Schwartz, versions of her curriculum vitae, and her date books from the 1950s through the 2000s.
The Electronic Materials File includes files received from Schwartz's office at the National Bureau of Economic Research office in New York City. The electronic materials cover professional and personal papers of Anna Schwartz, including correspondence, conference files, research files, writing drafts, writings, newspaper clippings, photos, and her bio/CV.
Money supply -- United States; Money -- United States; Gold standard -- United States; Structural adjustment (Economic policy) -- United States; Depressions -- History; Depressions -- 1929; Economic history -- United Kingdom; Economic history -- United States; Banks and banking; Monetary policy -- United States; Economists -- United States; Schwartz, Anna J. (Anna Jacobson), 1915-2012; Friedman, Milton, 1912-2006; Shadow Open Market Committee (U.S.); United States -- Economic conditions; United States. Federal Open Market Committee
- Correspondence, 1929-2012, 1 box
  Scope and Contents note
  The Correspondence series consists of professional correspondence from throughout Schwartz's career. Materials include handwritten, typed, and email correspondence, with the bulk of the material dating from late in Schwartz's career. Email printouts of articles and other email forwards from Schwartz's contacts are also present in this series. Early correspondence includes courtship letters from Schwartz's husband, Isaac. Correspondence with or directly concerning Milton Friedman is filed in the "Correspondence" subseries within the "Milton Friedman" series.
  - Correspondence, 1929-1950s (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1960s (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1970s (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1980s (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1990-1995 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1996-1997 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1998-1999 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 2000-2002 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 2003-2005 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 2006-2007 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 2008, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 2009 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 2010-2012 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 1)
- Personal Materials, 1933-2012, 2 boxes
  The Personal Materials Series contains materials from Schwartz's college years at Barnard, decades of daybooks with calendars from her various meetings, Schwartz's handwritten phone logs from the early 1980s, resumes, honorary degree materials, and clippings about Schwartz from the 1960s through the 2000s.
  - Barnard College materials, 1933-1934 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous personal materials (Box 1)
  - Datebooks, 1950s-1970s, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Datebooks, 1980s-2000s, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Phone logs, 1981 and undated (Box 2)
  - Resume/c.v., 1988 and 2007 (Box 2)
  - Clippings and interviews about Schwartz, 1960s-2000s, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Honorary degrees, 2000s (Box 2)
- Conferences, 1964-2008, 1 box
  The Conferences series contains materials from Schwartz's conference participation. Conferences are arranged alphabetically. The series includes programs, correspondence concerning specific events, and copies of speeches given by other participants.
  - Alex G. McKenna Economic Education Series, St. Vincent College, 30 April 1999 (Box 2)
  - American Bankers Association - Conference for University Professors, 1964 (Box 2)
  - American Economic Association, 1984 and 2001, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - American Enterprise Institute, 1998 and 2000, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - American Finance Association, 2001 (Box 2)
  - American Institute for Economic Research, 2004-2005, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - AMEX Monetary Unions Conference, 1999 (Box 2)
  - Asset Price Bubble Conference, 2001-2002, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Bank of England Conference, 2004 (Box 2)
  - Capital Markets Colloquium, Duke University, 2007 (Box 2)
  - Carnegie Rochester Conference, 1999 (Box 2)
  - CATO Institute Annual Monetary Conference, 1997, 1999, 2002-2003, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Colloquium on Globalization, UCLA, 1999 (Box 2)
  - Conference in Honor of Milton Friedman's 60th Birthday: scrapbook pages with photographs (Box 18)
  - Conference in Honor of Walter Y. Oi, University of Rochester, 1999 (Box 2)
  - Council on Foreign Relations, 2000 and 2004, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - ECU Conference, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Federal Reserve Bank of Atlanta Conference on Financial Markets, 1999 (Box 2)
  - Federal Reserve Bank of Chicago Conferences, 1988 and 1999, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Federal Reserve Bank of New York: Financial Innovation and Monetary Transmission, 2001 (Box 2)
  - Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis: Economic Policy Conference, 2007 (Box 2)
  - Goodhart Festschrift, 2001 (Box 2)
  - History of Economic Thought, 1998 (Box 2)
  - How to Manage Capital in a World of Permanent Inflation, 1973 (Box 2)
    Includes Schwartz's talk, The Inflation Experience of Other Countries, 1973.
  - International Atlantic Economic Society Meeting, 2002 (Box 2)
  - Money, History, and International Finance: Conference Held in Honor of Anna J. Schwartz, 1987: photograph album (Box 18)
  - National Bureau of Economic Research conferences, 1986, 1993, 2001, 2008, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Political Economy of International Finance, 2000 (Box 2)
  - Social Science Research Council Conference on the Federal Reserve Board, 1965 (Box 2)
  - U. Beogradu Symposium, 1974 (Box 2)
  - World Conference on Gold, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Western Economic Association, 1984 and 2000 (Box 2)
    Includes VHS interview of Schwartz, 1984. This item is RESTRICTED until an access copy can be made.
- Subject and Research Files, 5 boxes
  This series contains Schwartz's research files on various subjects, comprised of notes, data and tables, and printed materials related to specific topics; some are related directly to specific publications. It is arranged alphabetically by subject. Topics that receive the most coverage include the 2008 financial crisis; banking; business cycles; currency boards; the FDIC, FOMC, and Federal Reserve; gold; the IMF; intervention; and UK economics. There are also a number of files containing worksheets and data from the NBER.
  - 2008 Financial Crisis, 9 folders (Box 3)
  - American Institute for Economic Research (Box 3)
  - Argentina, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Asian Monetary Monitor (Box 3)
  - Asset prices (Box 3)
  - Austria-Hungary (Box 3)
  - Bank of America (Box 3)
  - Bank capital (Box 3)
  - Bank loan loss deduction (Box 3)
  - Bank money computation: P. Cagan: Postal deposits with U.S. Treasury (Box 3)
  - Bank of England (Box 3)
  - Bank of the United States (Box 3)
  - Bank runs (Box 3)
  - Banking (Box 3)
  - Banking supervision, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Banks, savings and loan (Box 3)
  - Brazil and Mexico (Box 3)
  - Business cycle research, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Charts and graphs, miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Congressional oversight panel for economic stabilization, 2008 (Box 3)
  - Congressional Record (Box 3)
  - Currency (Box 3)
  - Currency boards, 8 folders (Box 3)
  - Currency boards, 8 folders (Box 4)
  - Exchange Stabilization Fund (ESF), 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Exchange rate policy (Box 4)
  - FDIC and FDIC reform, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Federal Open Market Committee (FOMC), 13 folders (Box 4)
    Includes meeting minutes and transcripts.
  - Federal Reserve Board, 15 folders (Box 5)
  - Foreign currency, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Foreign exchange rates (Box 5)
  - Free banking, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Free gold (Box 5)
  - Gold, 5 folders (Box 5)
  - International Monetary Fund (IMF), 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Intervention, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Intervention, 4 folders (Box 6)
    Includes History of Foreign Exchange Market Invention project notes.
  - Interwar world trade (Box 6)
  - Ireland (Box 6)
  - Italy (Box 6)
  - Japan (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous Newsletters and Printouts (Box 6)
  - Monetarism, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Monetary Control Act of 1980 (Box 6)
  - Monetary policy, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Money stock, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - National Bureau of Economic Research (NBER), 12 folders (Box 6)
  - Notes, handwritten, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Reforming financial markets (Box 6)
  - Reserves: Actual versus Required (Box 6)
  - Shadow Financial Regulatory Committee, 1989-1998, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - System Open Market Account (SOMA), 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Sovereign bankruptcy (Box 7)
  - Supreme Court: Petitioner's Brief, Samson Taiwo Dada (Box 7)
  - Treasury Select Committee, 2009 (Box 7)
  - United Kingdom, 5 folders (Box 7)
  - U.S. Senate, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - U.S. stabilization agreements (Box 7)
  - Vault cash worksheets (Box 7)
  - Harry Dexter White (Box 7)
- Writings, 1953-2009, 2 boxes
  The Writings series is arranged chronologically and consists of Schwartz's lectures and publications (some of which are co-authored) as well as drafts of both published and unpublished pieces. Materials related to Schwartz's publications, such as book reviews and edits, are also included under the title of that publication. A significant part of the series consists of drafts of A History of Official Foreign Exchange Market Intervention, a manuscript on which Schwartz was collaborating with Michael Bordo and Owen Humpage. Small amounts of correspondence directly related to the publication of various works is filed with those works. Projects on which Schwartz collaborated with Milton Friedman are in the "Milton Friedman" series; research for various writing projects can be found in the "Subject Files and Research" series.
  - Book reviews by Schwartz, 1984-2007 (Box 7)
  - State Banks, 1942, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Growth and Fluctuation reviews, 1953-1954 and 1971 (Box 7)
  - Untitled manuscript draft and appendices, 1982 (Box 7)
  - The Service Flows of Money drafts, 1984-1985 (Box 7)
  - A European Central Bank, 1990 (Box 7)
  - Currency Boards, 1993 (Box 7)
  - The Performance of the Federal Research in Pursuing International Monetary Objectives, 1994 (Box 7)
  - The Performance and Stabilization of Banking Systems Under Self-Regulation, 1995 (Box 7)
    Co-authored with Michael Bordo.
  - European Monetary Union, 1996 (Box 7)
  - Mexican Loan Repayment Sleight of Hand, 1996 (Box 7)
  - From Obscurity to Notoriety, 1997 (Box 7)
  - Central Banking in a Democracy, 1997 (Box 7)
  - Time to Terminate the ESF and IMF, 1998 (Box 7)
  - Declaration for Lawsuit Challenging the Mexican Bailout of 1995, 1998 (Box 7)
  - What Europe Can Learn from the Fed, Wall Street Journal, 1998 (Box 7)
  - Monetary Policy Reforms, 1999 (Box 7)
  - Measuring Real Economic Effects of Bailouts, 1999, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - The Rise and Fall of Foreign Exchange Market Intervention as a Policy Tool, 2000 (Box 7)
  - Was Expansionary Monetary Policy Feasible During the Great Contraction? An Examination of Gold Standard Constraint, 2000 (Box 7)
    Co-authored with Michael Bordo and Choundhri.
  - From the Exchange Stabilization Fund to the International Monetary Fund, 2001 (Box 7)
  - Comment on the Optimal Choice of Exchange-Rate Regime, 2001 (Box 7)
  - Earmarks of a Lender of Last Resort, 2001-2002 (Box 7)
  - The IMF's Dubious Proposal for a Universal Bankruptcy Law for Sovereign Debtors, 2003 (Box 8)
  - Aftermath of the Monetarist Clash with the Federal Reserve Before and During the Volcker Era, 2004 (Box 8)
  - Bretton Woods, 2004 (Box 8)
  - Global Order and the Future of the Euro, 2004 (Box 8)
  - Dealing with Exchange Rate Protectionism, 2005 (Box 8)
  - Gold, Policy Expectations, and Financial Markets During the Great Depression, 2005 (Box 8)
  - Money Supply, 2005-2007 (Box 8)
  - David Laidler on Monetarism, 2006 (Box 8)
  - Globalization, 2007 (Box 8)
  - Is there a need for an International Lender of Last Resort?, 2007 (Box 8)
  - Is Redefinition Needed of the Aims of the Mont Pelerin Society 60 Years After Their Formation?, 2007 (Box 8)
  - Why a Dual Mandate is Wrong For Monetary Policy, 2008 (Box 8)
    Co-authored with Walker Todd. Also known as "The Confusion of Nominal Monetary Policies and Real Outcomes at the Federal Reserve."
  - Monetary Economics Research at the St. Louis Fed During Ted Balbach's Tenure as Research Director, 2008 (Box 8)
  - Questions the Senate Finance Committee Could have Asked T. Geithner and the Answers He Should have Given, 2009 (Box 8)
  - General collaborations with Walker Todd, 1990-2009 (Box 8)
  - How to Avoid an International Financial Crisis, undated (Box 8)
  - How the Relationship between the Federal Reserve and the Academic Community of Monetary Economists Has Changed Over Time, undated (Box 8)
  - Has the Fed Forgotten the Lessons of the Peace Time Inflation of 1965-1979?, undated (Box 8)
  - The Fed in the 1920s and 1930s, undated (Box 8)
  - Monetarism, undated (Box 8)
  - Origins of the Financial Market Crisis of 2008, undated (Box 8)
  - What Future for the IMF?, undated (Box 8)
  - My Answers to your Questions, undated (Box 8)
  - History of Foreign Exchange Market Intervention materials, with Michael Bordo, 2006-2007 and undated, 29 folders (Box 8)
  - Incomplete pieces of writings and articles, undated (Box 8)
  - Contracts and agreements, 2004-2009 (Box 8)
- Gold Commission, 1974-1985, 2 boxes
  This series covers Schwartz's work with Gold Commission, which was appointed to consider the possibility of returning to the gold standard. Schwartz was the Staff Director from 1981-1982. The series includes transcripts and minutes; memos; statements and testimonials given before the commission; questionnaires filled out by members of the commission; correspondence sent to and within the commission; and research files (articles, reports, notes, and data tables).
  - Transcripts, 1981-1982, 4 folders (Box 9)
  - Memos, 1981-1982, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - November 1981 statements before the Gold Commission, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - December 1981 questionnaire (Box 9)
  - Statements, 1980-1981 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous papers (Box 9)
  - Publicity and clippings (Box 9)
  - Gold Commission Report outline (Box 9)
  - Report of the Commission on the Role of Gold in the Domestic and International Monetary Systems, volumes 1 and 2, March 1982 (Box 9)
  - Report suggestions, recommendations, and comments, 5 folders (Box 9)
  - Report suggestions, recommendations, and comments (Box 10)
  - Report suggestions, recommendations, and comments from Chalmers P. Wylie (Box 10)
  - Gold Commission proposal with edits (Box 10)
  - Consolidated gold fields - limited reports, 1974-1981, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Committee on Interior and Exterior Affairs on Feasibility of Return to Gold Standard, 1980 (Box 10)
  - Thomas Wolfe, "Report on World Production, Marketing, and Use of Gold," undated, and "Structure of World Gold Stocks," 1977 (Box 10)
  - David Glasner, "A Reinterpretation of Classical Monetary Theory," 1982-1983 (Box 10)
  - Edgar Schoen, The Undisciplined Dollar, 1980 (Box 10)
  - Data from Ramachandra Bhagavatula, 1981 (Box 10)
  - Gold Commission articles, 1952-1984 and undated (Box 10)
  - Gold Commission reports and articles, 1974-1985 (Box 10)
  - Articles on the gold standard, 1978-1985 and undated (Box 10)
  - Articles on the gold standard, 1979-1980 (Box 10)
  - Reports, 1981 (Box 10)
  - "Gold in International Monetary Law," Journal of International Law and Economics, 1981 (Box 10)
  - Gold Commission notes (Box 10)
  - Tables and reports (Box 10)
  - Data and tables, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1 June 1981-1982 and undated, 4 folders (Box 10)
- Shadow Open Market Committee, 1998-2006, 1 box
  This series documents Schwartz's participation in the Shadow Open Market Committee, which was founded in 1973 to independently evaluate and critique the actions of the Federal Reserve's Open Market Committee. The series contains materials from the biannual meetings, including folders, programs, research, notes, and papers presented by Schwartz and other members, from 2000 to 2006, as well as a 2002 article about the SOMC.
  - European Shadow Financial Regulatory Committee statements, 1998-1999 (Box 11)
  - 13 November 2000 meeting (Box 11)
  - 30 April 2001 meeting (Box 11)
  - 14-15 October 2001 meeting (Box 11)
  - 14-15 April 2002 meeting (Box 11)
  - 18 November 2002 meeting (Box 11)
  - 2002 meeting data (Box 11)
  - 18-19 May 2003 meeting (Box 11)
  - 2 May 2004 meeting (Box 11)
  - 14-15 November 2004 meeting (Box 11)